Greetings and welcome, my name is Jake
Rayson, I am a wildlife and food
forest garden designer and welcome to my
online class ‘CAD for Gardeners’, this is
a beginner's guide so this is aimed
at beginners but also people who are keen
to get cracking really quickly with using
computer aided design for their garden creations
A couple of notes before we get started. First
of all this slideshow is always available
online natureworks.org.uk/class/cad
If you press the key `P` on
your keyboard, it brings up all the
notes and there’s some interesting links and
extra information in there as well
So without further ado let’s get cracking
An outline for today - why CAD?
why would you bother using CAD in
the first place? Indeed, why would you
bother planning in the first place? And
then I’m going to look at setting
up QCAD and QCAD is the
software that I use for CAD designs
Going through step by step
on how to set it up so that it
all works nicely
The third section is looking at shapes
entities and mods. Basically the simple
shapes, there’s four simple shapes that if you
learn, you can create an infinite variety
of shapes by combining them, and using
entities to rotate stuff, and modifications to
alter all these different elements as well
So we’ll be
learning four basic shapes, three types of
entity and four modifications. And then finally
I’ll be looking at two examples, a
one acre garden and a town
garden and I’ll be walking through
step-by-step how to create them. So
why CAD?
A very good question! A bit of background first
of all. There is, as you might
well be aware, a nature and climate
emergency and gardens need to be a
wildlife haven with crops, with edible crops
I will give you a definition of
what a forest garden is because that’s my
gardening background
But I think in general terms
this world needs more gardeners and it
needs more gardeners who are aware of
the issues surrounding the nature and
the climate emergency, so changing conditions and
a massive, massive, massive decrease in the
in the number of species. This is
why we need all of this
new gardens to be planned and that’s
where the CAD side comes in
because it can make the process a
lot easier. So what is a forest
garden, I’ll just give you an overview
A forest garden
to quote Martin Crawford's fantastic book which
I refer to all the
time, Martin Crawford is a great
chap down in Devon and been creating
forest gardens for years and years and
years, and this is a bit of
a bible. It goes through a
whole range of different processes for setting
up a forest garden and all the
load of different species as well
And as he says, ‘it’s working with
nature to grow edible crops’ and this
is a photograph here from his garden
in Devon and what we’re doing is
to emulate the edge of woodland because
you want to have crops in the
understory and you want to have enough light
coming through. So it’s not thick dense
woodland, it’s the edge of woodland and
then you have different layers of plants
occupying that space. And it’s a
very good system because it uses
natural pest control and fertility, so you
grow all your fertility on site. So
essentially what you’re doing is to create
an edible ecosystem. What is CAD? I’m
very
glad you asked it is Computer Aided
Design. That’s a link there to the
Wikipedia article. Basically it’s a
line based drawing package; you’re creating precise
line diagrams and it’s used mostly in
architecture and manufacturing, where you need a
great deal of precision we don’t really
need that precision in gardening. It’s
kind of useful but that’s not the
the major reason for using it. If
you compare it to drawing programs like
Adobe Illustrator and Inkscape, the massive difference is
that CAD is far, far more scalable
and far faster. It doesn’t look as
pretty but it does, in my humble
opinion, it does the job a lot better
And we’re looking at 2D CAD, two
dimensional CAD, and this basically means that
it’s just in two dimensions
viewing it from above, and that’s a
plan view. I use Open Source CAD
a package called QCAD which I absolutely
love. It’s brilliant, really lovely piece
of software. Open Source software
means the code for the software is
freely available online and the very
cool thing is that the price is
so much cheaper than any kind of
commercial software. The industry standard Vectorworks costs
£1,230
per year, it’s a subscription model, and
that
is just kind of outrageous and
to be honest, the free version of
QCAD is more than adequate for
CAD garden design. There is an alternative
to QCAD which is totally free called
LibreCAD and there’s a link in
the notes. I actually pay for the
paid version of QCAD, I paid about
£41
I think it is and the
reason for that really is to support
the developer because you have something which
is a good piece of software you want
the developer to keep on
working at it and to fix any
bugs and progress with it
There is a QCAD book as
well. Totally recommend getting that book, even
with the free version because there’s a
whole load of
information, there’s a lot of detail
there’s quite a stuff that you won’t
need but I’ll go through today showing
you the key points and you can
refer to them in the book
Do you even need CAD? You might
be better off using paper
if you’re only doing one design and
you’re not that comfortable using computers
5mm graph paper is
really good, I mean it’s a really
really good medium and it’s far freer
and in a lot of ways more flexible than
CAD but it’s not as easy to
work with if you’re working in a
group. This is the
5mm
grid that you can see there!
If you’re working with a group of
people or people who are distributed around geographically
you actually might be better off learning
CAD. Whatever you do use, get the
scale right. really really important to always
get the scale right. So that anything that
you add, any elements that you add
later on, will fit into that
And if you click on this image
it gives you a higher resolution, isn't
that fantastic?
So the CAD pros are that it’s
1:1 within the program itself
and what this means is you don’t
have to scale the drawing in the
software. If you’re creating a twenty metre
by twenty metre garden, you draw it as
twenty metres by twenty metres in the
software. This is as compared to using
Adobe Illustrator
where you have to scale
the drawing down, otherwise it slows the
program up too much. And that’s the
other thing about CAD as well, it’s
super fast. I run it on really
really ancient old PCs and it’s great
It’s just really really fast and it’s
accurate. It can slow down
if you’ve got thousands of plants on
there but there’s no need to worry
about the power of your PC. And
it’s easy to edit, as compared to
a paper plan where it can get
messy, and the more elements that you
have on a paper plan, and the
more you move things around the messier
it can get, whether you’re working with overlays
or whether you’re rubbing things out or
you’ve got little cutout bits of paper
to represent plants -
that can get a little bit
messy whereas you don’t have that with
using CAD. And it’s portable as well
This means that you can easily email
people a CAD file and you can
print it out as a PDF file
a Portable Document Format, and email that
to people too
The cons of using CAD are that it
is technical. I won’t lie to you
there is a steep learning curve to
it. You’ve got to put the hours
in to learn the software. But once
you do, and this is why it’s
worth it if you’re creating more than
one design, once you do master those
essential skills, then your workflow will
be much
quicker. And it is ugly. It’s not
designed to look pretty. So a nice
thing about Adobe Illustrator is that you
can create lots of shading and
different styles
But to be honest, if that’s what
you want to do, I would actually
suggest doing that within CAD and then
exporting that and then bringing that into
a different program to make it look prettier
Reasons to plan. In my book
there are five main reasons to plan
whether you’re using CAD or whether you’re
using paper. The first of these is
to get the spacing
right. In a forest garden, as
I mentioned before, the idea is to emulate
the edge of woodland, so you want
to have enough light coming through for
the understory and getting that spacing between
the trees is really really essential. That’s
like the main framework of the garden
design. The second reason is the position
and positioning of the
plants and positioning of the different features
within the garden and it’s much easier
with a plan to get an overview
of what’s going on in different parts
of the garden and how they relate to
each other
The third reason is quantity. CAD is absolutely
brilliant at calculating areas and lengths and you
can calc, from that you can work
out the quantity of plants that you require. Fourth
reason is communicate, so you’re communicating with
clients and you’re communicating with other people
you’re working with, whether that’s landscapers or
people who are putting the
plants out. And then finally documenting. Once
you’ve created your garden, it’s always
a good idea to know where things are
So tree spacing. This is an
illustration which has been inspired by Martin
Crawford’s book and this is tree spacing
within a forest garden. Martin Crawford
recommends
tree spacing of quarter to a half
of the average canopy diameter. So for
example you’ve got two 4 metre
diameter trees, then the tree spacing that
you want between them is 1 to
2 metres and that’s because you want
to get enough light coming through
Position
This is because a plan will enable
you to play with ideas far more
easily. If you’re trying to do it all
from memory, it could be hard to
remember where different things are. If you’ve
got a large site and you’re out
on site you can have great ideas
but it’s having somewhere to put all
those ideas. So it also
enables you, a plan, to try these
different positions quickly, so you can put
a tree in one place and then
put it into a totally opposite corner
of the garden very very quickly. And
it gives you an overview of the
different conditions within that garden, so like
where the water is or where the
light is rising and the sun
is setting
CAD is absolutely brilliant at working out
estimates, so you can figure out the
quantities of plants. This is a screenshot
from a design that I did for
a relatively small garden locally, and you
can see there’s an area here called Curve
it’s a kind of curved bed
and I can work
out really quickly that that’s 6
metres square. Likewise, there’s a line measuring
tool as well. And once you’ve got
an area and you know what your
planting density is, then it’s easy to
calculate how many plants you need. Likewise
if you’re planning a hedge, you know
how long that hedge is going to
be and you’ve got your planting
density for the
hedging plants then it’s again
very easy to calculate the quantities required
So, it works really really well with
a spreadsheet. For each of my
clients I create an online spreadsheet of
all the different plants and then I
can work out quantities from that and prices
from that as well
The fourth reason to create a plan
is the ability to communicate and that’s
sharing ideas with partners, whether that’s clients
or other people that you’re working with
Really, a plan is like itself a
landscaping and a planting guide, so you’ve
got any hard landscaping that you need
doing, any paths that need to be
put in or fencing, then people will
know the lengths and the dimensions. And
likewise with the planting guide, people know the
quantities of plants that need to be
put in and what densities are going
in at. And I always kind of
create online notes for each my clients
and then I can share a
PDF of the plan
and the original CAD file with
with my clients that way, so they’ll
see it. And a plan is fantastic
as a guide for your future self
as well, so very often you think
you’ll know what you’re doing with the
design and what you’re doing with the
planting but if you write it down
is like an aide de memoire, it really
really helps. So, your future self will
thank you if you do
create a plan. The fifth reason is
to document your planting. Where on
earth did you put those plants? I’m
sure everyone's had this before in the
past, you can’t remember what plant is
in which bed, so if you have
a plan, it then changes the process and
it becomes a document that you can
refer to and it tells you where
your plants are. And don’t forget like
the seasonal differences in the middle of
winter then all herbaceous perennials would
have died down so they're not going to
be so visible. It’s also a really
good document to educate the partners with
And management is a top priority, even
though it’s at the bottom of the
the list. I think working out how
a garden will be cared for and
managed long-term is really really important. So
if you’ve got a document in
the form of a plan that gives
a client something to work from