Greetings and welcome back to the third
section of my online class ‘CAD for
Gardeners’ and this is shapes, entities and
mods, you can just about see
the mods, my face is nearly covering
it, and here I’m going to be
looking at four basic shapes, three entity
types and then four modifications
that you can make. And using
these tools, you can create a whole
infinite variety of different designs, hopefully. First
of all, before going further, I wanted
to say about finding your way
around QCAD because it can be a
little bit confusing. So I’m just going
to zip over to QCAD
I’ll create a new file, I’m
just going to create a circle and
really worry too much about what I’m
doing here…
The great thing as I said before
about QCAD is that you can
zoom in and you can zoom out
and it can be two hundred miles
wide or it can be twenty centimetres
wide. The QCAD doesn’t really matter
it’s kind of 1:1 scale
and you work at whatever size
the thing is that you’re working on
Erm…
so for zooming in, zooming out, there’s
the mouse scroll. Sorry, that’s a really
really bad pun. That is a mouse
with a scroll, took ages to
find that one. Mouse scroll will zoom
you in and out so the mouse
scroll is that button there and that
will zoom you in and out in CAD. The plus
or minus keys on your keyboard
Snd then if you get lost, it’s
`View > Zoom > Auto Zoom` and that will
get you back to where
your drawing is. I’ll just show you what
I mean. So mouse scroll first of
all, so mouse scroll, zoom in and
you can zoom in, zoom in and
zoom in and zoom in and and
it’s just incredible how much you
can zoom in
until your screen is filled with
a line. Then you can zoom out
as well and you can zoom out
and the problem with this zooming
in, zooming out, plus minus keys
minus, plus… oopsie, the problem
is, it’s actually really really easy to
get lost and I’ve got no idea
where my circle’s gone. So if you
go to `View` menu and then `Zoom`
and zoom auto, `Auto Zoom` which has
`ZA` as the
keyboard shortcut. It’s kinda nice to use
keyboard shortcuts because it speeds things up
but don’t worry about it. So click
on `Auto Zoom`, wmf, it brings your
drawing into full view. So if you’re
zooming in and zooming out, you don’t
know where you are, click `View > Zoom >
Auto Zoom` and it brings you straight
back. I’ll just do it again, `View >
Zoom > Auto Zoom` it brings you
straight back. Okay? The next
thing is panning, so with panning
that means kind of scrubbing or
moving across the screen
So that’s a mouse scroll click, so
again the mouse scroll button and then click
it down and then you
can pan around the document
or `View > Zoom > Pan Zoom`, so holding
down the mouse scroll you know
you can
pan across like that or `View > Zoom >
Pan Zoom` and that enables you to
scroll down and get really really dizzy
So the next bit that I wanted
to show you was what what happens
if you kind of get lost at all
The thing to remember, is don’t
panic
So there’s two ways that I can
get lost. Firstly, as I said before
is zooming and zooming out, so
that’s `View > Zoom > Auto Zoom`, so if
I don’t know where I am and
I can’t see anything, `ZA`, bof!
Brings it straight back. The other thing
is, if I’ve started clicking on different
tools and I don’t know how to
get back to the pointer, just hit
the escape key and that returns you
to the arrow tool. So, just keep
hitting it and eventually you’ll get back
to the pointer tool and
then get back to square one, okay
So those two tools are really really useful
to get back to
your drawing and also to get back
to your arrow
Right, so next up is shapes
entities and mods. As I said, four
shapes, three entities and four mods. What
you want to do, press the `P`
key again, you want to download the files
from here. This is the CAD
gardener’s files and I’ll just show you
where you get them from
So this is where the files are
stored and the files are in a
folder called `cad-shapes-entities-mods`, probably
the easiest thing to do is download them
altogether, so if you click on the
`Code` button and then `Download zip`, unzip
it and then you’ve got the CAD
files that you can play around with
First thing then that we’re going to
do
is to look at creating the four
shapes. So you’ve got a rectangle, line
tool, circles for trees and NURBS for
curves. How terribly exciting. So rectangle is under
the `Shape Tools` in the
toolbar menu and the two rectangles that I
use all the time, there’s like one
which is just drawing a rectangle, so
yeah, I know that it
will be drawn like that
Hit escape key, back for the pointer and
it draws a rectangle
made out of lines
And the other one that I use
probably a lot more, is the rectangle
with size and this is actually really
useful. So say I’ve got a, oh I don’t
know, I’ve got a shed that’s
3 metres by 2 metres
I kind of just put the size
in, along the top here
and then there we go, it’s
a shed which is fantastic. So
that’s a rectangle tool. We use rectangles
mostly for structures in a garden, so
sheds, some polytunnels and steps and
stuff like that. The next tool is
the line tool. So hit `Escape` to go
back to the arrow tool
click on `Line Tools` and I only ever
use one line tool and that is
this one here, which is `Line from
2 Points`. And I just go… pom-ti-dom…
create a line like
that. And a line tools good for kind
of irregular non-rectilinear shapes and it’s also
really really good for
for creating
paths, for example, so you don’t have
to use NURBS, you don’t have to
create curvy paths, if you
want to just for quickness
you can create a basic path like
that, yeah, so that’s the kind of
thing that you can use it for
as well. And then creating boundaries. I’ll
be going through all these when I
do the examples as well, to give
you some real world
examples. The third shape is
a circle and again, the circle tool, and
I only ever create, it’s all
these different options, it’s mind blowing
how many different options there are and what
you can do with them and tangents
and all sorts of stuff, but I
only ever use one circle and that’s
circles for trees, so you click
there
we go, and that tool is called
let’s just make sure I’ve got the right name, `Center
Point`, so you draw a circle from the
point and there we go and you
can just draw circles for trees. And this
is where the `Property` widget comes in
really really handy because what you can
do, select the shape and then say
oh
I don’t know, there’s a Sweet Chestnut
is roughly 15 metres diameter, if you
look in the `Property Editor` under diameter
down here on the right hand side
and then type in 15, there you
go, that’s the diameter of a Sweet
Chestnut. And then I can say ‘Oh
right then, I want to create another
one’. And this is going to be
4 metres wide because that’s the diameter
Select, draw the circle, select it, diameter
And that’s the diameter of an apple
tree on an MM106
rootstock, for example. So now you’ve got
circles for trees, and then you can
work out, using the tree spacing, you
can calculate the distance actually it
should be between the trees. And
finally, NURBS. I wasn't going to show
show you NURBS but they’re so great
that’s such a brilliant name, it
stands for Non-Uniform Rational B-Splines
I think. Have a play and
if you like them and get on
with them, then use them. Again, I only
ever use one spline tool, this one
at the top, spline with control points
And you can click, click, click, double-
click to stop the drawing, escape
to get the arrow tool back and
then you’ve got a control point, which
is here, which is fantastic
There we go and then obviously
you can create a lot more complex shapes
so if you’re creating a path, it’s a
wibbly wobbly path, you can do
all sorts of great, great, great fun
stuff
This is a really good moment to
talk about the snap tool because this
makes your life an awful lot easier
So what it’s set to by default
when you create a shape, let’s go
back and get a line tool because it’ll
be probably easier, it’s snapping to the
grid
or it’s snapping on an intersection
and that’s the default behavior. So it
kind of guesses where you want
to snap to which is great but
sometimes you say ‘I want it just
over here’ and it’s not enough
you want to make a free play
sort of thing for your snapping and
the way to do that is to
use `Snap Free`. So if you go
to the `Snap`
menu and then go `Snap Free`
or `SF` is a shortcut, then
it’s not snapping to anything
at all. So it means it won’t
snap onto a line. So it depends
what you’re trying
to achieve. I don’t know, like if you’ve
got a curvy curvy path that
you want to make then you
don’t really want to have it snapping
directly to a grid or directly to another object
Sometimes you do want it to snap
so for example if I wanted to
close this shape, I want it to snap
on the corner but it’s not going
to, it’s just going to do it a
little bit away. So `Snap Free`
really very useful for freehand stuff
And then the other one that you
want
quite commonly is `Snap On Entity`, which
is `ST`, so get a line tool
and I say okay, I know that
I want to snap onto the rectangle
somewhere, see, it’s auto-snapping
here, you can see it’s auto-snapping
to the middle and auto-snapping to
the intersection but I want it to
snap on the actual entity
itself, like on this circle
for example. If I go `Snap On
Entity`
then it will glue itself to that
entity. And I want to
take it off, I can go `Snap Auto`
`Snap Auto` down here, and then it’s
going back to automatically snapping
to the grid or to the end
of something else. So that’s a
really really handy one. The final
snap is `Snap to End`, so this is
great if you’ve got a shape and
you say I want to
close this shape here
so it’s like a closed
shape
So what you do there, get the
line tool and
you can click, snap, and just to
make sure it snaps on end you
go `Snap on End`, bomf! It
won’t snap anywhere else and you’re guaranteed
that that shape is enclosed now. So
these snapping facilities are really really useful
it’s really handy to know
them. And it’s, yeah, just be aware
that you’ve got the snap menu
there and then you can use the
snapping tools as and when you see
fit. So when it comes up, you
go ‘Why won’t this
line go here?’ and you can figure out
whether it needs to be `Snap Auto`
or `Snap Free` or `Snap Entity` or
`Snap to the End`
Okay, let’s get onto the entities. We’ve
got three entities, that’s block, polyline and
text, and they're all pretty
cool in their own special ways. A
block is really really useful if you’re
creating a symbol. It can be re-used
over and over again. So for example
you have an orchard and it’s
got a lot of the same apple
trees in it. You can just make
one apple tree and then plant lots
of different instances around. When you edit
the one block, it changes all those
instances. But it’s also useful for creating
a shape and then applying any angle
So in this example I’ve created a
bench
and I’ve then created an angle
on it. I’ll show you how to
do that. So hit escape to go
back to the arrow tool, go click
onto the shape tools and I’ll
just create any old rectangle
And rather than, what you can
do, if you go into the shape
tools and then shape with
sizes, you can put an angle in
here but then it’s much harder once
you’ve created that angle. Once you’ve created
that shape, it’s much much harder to
edit it. So you’re better off creating
it so that it’s
square and *then* applying the angle afterwards
So I’ll just show you how to
create a block, so you select all
those
elements, go to the `Block` menu and
then `Create Block From Selection` and then
you say where you want to create
it from, sets the corner, and I’m
going to call it, I don’t know, shed
And down here in the `Block List`
on the right hand side you can see
shed comes up and then I can
have multiple sheds
and I can put sheds down all
over the place. Hooray. So now, for
example, I want to edit it, I’m
gonna say I want to
I don’t know, colour the lines
make the lines a different colour, I’ll
make them green
And then go out, and so now I’ve
got green sheds all over the place
But if I just want to rotate
one of my sheds, I can go
here and I’ll just give it an
angle in the `Properties`, it’s 45 degrees
type in 45 degrees and just
that instance has
changed so that’s really kind of, yeah
it’s really really handy and then you
can make sure that you get the
right angle and it’s much much easier
to control. Cool
The other entity that I want to
talk about was the polyline and these
are great. Best way to show you
this is with the line tool so
go for the line tool
and I’ll create kind of
linage thing, wibbly wobbly line, eeeh!
And that’s great and you go well that’s
fantastic
but the pain in the bum is
that I have to create a shift
click every single item before I want
to move it or have to select
them all by dragging it like that
and that can be a bit painful
So it’s much better
or you can double-click and it
will select the whole shape, but unless
the shape then is touching
something else it’ll select all that as
well, so much much better to create
a polyline of that line. So
create a polyline, dom-dom, double-click to
select all of them and you go
`Draw > Polyline >
Polyline From Selection` and I am constantly
amazed at the number of different options
that we’ve got but just concentrate, all
you have to do is concentrate on
the ones I’m giving you and
that to be honest these are all
the only ones I ever use myself
So `Polyline From Selection`, there we go
now, wow, look, it treats it as a
whole kind of group
And what it also does, if you
click on it, it will give you
an area, so try and work out
what that area is
Another handy tool, if you’ve got a
polyline, then you want to explode it. This
really ought to be in modifications but
there’s a bomb here, set off that
stick of dynamite, boff! it explodes it and
what I want to do now is
to close that line, so hit
escape key
to go back to the arrow tool
click on the line tool and I’m
going to close that shape and now
you can imagine, double-click, create a
polyline from that and you can say
yep, that is now a garden bed
and I know that by clicking on
it, this is about the garden bed
is
about 5 metres diameter [square!] and with a
planting density of 5 plants per square
metre, that’s 25 plants, thank you
very much. So this is where it
comes in really really useful using these
different tools. And then finally the last
entity that I wanted to discuss is
text tool
And it kinda does what it says
on the tin really, enables you to
put labels on things which is handy
if you want to know what the
trees are that you’re using
or what a particular structure is so
double-click
and then escape to go back to
the tool menu and arrow tool and
I’m going to click on the text
tool. Click on `Text` and it brings up
the whole lot here. For some reason
I always colour my text orange I
think it’s a middle
of the road colour and fits in
with everything else. I’m going to call this shed
I’m gonna make it orange and think
it needs to be a bit smaller, there we go and
you’ve got lots of options. If you
double-click on the text on
the text itself it brings up the
text dialog box and you’ve got lots
of options for whether it aligns in
the center or in the middle so that’s
all kind of handy too. There we go
so shed, pop that there, escape from
the block so I’m editing the block
at the moment in the `Block List`
click on that and then you can see
it’s got shed at an angle, there we
go. So those are your three entities
What I wanted to show you
next is very quickly is layers. Layers
is a really really good way of
organising different information. So you have
one layer for areas, one layer for
structures, another layer for plants or trees
you get the idea so you can
organize it by different layers and
then you can give different colors to
each layer as well, which again helps
with organising all the different elements
There is on my GitHub website, you
can download a template so you can
just click down here and download the
zip and then open up that file
and it will give
you this which is a list
of all the layers and it’s also
got a handy little legend which I’ve premade
here as well, as a block
And I’ll be using this when I’m
going through the different examples too
And then finally we’ve got the mods, four
different modifications to make. I’ll just go
through them with you
So here we go, mods you’ve got
four different types. Now this example is
actually taken from a real world example
of a gabion. Gabions are those wire
cages with stones in. And it’s a
gabion horseshoe shape that I’m creating for the
local primary school. It’s like a seating
area
but a kind of sheltered seating area
So I’ll just go through how
I’ve created it
On the center point
I create a circle as the first thing
and the modification tools are under this
menu over here. Ahhh, modification tools you’ve
already seen the the dynamite stick, so
select the element
that you want to modify
and I’m going to use offset
I think which is this one
here `Offset (with Distance)`
Okay it’s just 0.5 metres
that’s how wide it is, I might make
a little bit narrower
0.4, 0.3 metres
say
there we go, you get the idea
Yeah, 0.3 metres, 30 centimetres
and there we go that’s an offset
and you can offset it either way
Okay? Now I’ll take that shape and I
want to put two lines on to
cut into it, so I’m going to
draw one line on one side and a
mirror onto the other side and
let’s do that
Hit escape to go back, line tool, draw
from the centre, draw out here
Hit escape again, go back, select it with
the arrow tool, go to the modification
tools and up here is the mirror
and then click on mirror and say you
want to here, that line there. And
I want to keep the original and
I want to just flip it over. Bomf
There we go, so that’s the mirror tool
so that’s really good if you’ve got
any kind of symmetrical shapes that you
want to create and you can
mirror them. And now we go onto the
divide tool, this is always a great
deal of fun so you can see
what I’m trying to achieve here at
the end is to cut where
those lines intersect
So go back, hit escape key
to go back to the arrow tool
modification tools and then it’s the scissor
tool, which is great, nice
and easy and for the inner circle
click on the divide tool, the red pair of scissors
click on the inner circle, intersection
and intersection
select that segment, click delete, there you
go. And a really handy hint
if you are doing any drawing at all
with the line tool, rather than have
to redraw the line, using the snap
the automatic snap, you select the end
of the line and it will snap automatically
to the intersection with that circle. So
that’s very often the kind of quickest
way of creating the shape is to
use your existing lines and let the
snap do the work for you, like
that and there we go, we’ve got horseshoe
shape. I’ll turn that to make life
easier I’m going to turn this into a
block and I’ll
select all the items, all the elements
in there, `Block > Create Block From Selection`
click in the centre
and I’m going to call that, oh
I don’t know, horsehoe or something
And there we go, we’ve got a block
and just makes that easier, creating a
block makes it easy to rotate so that
you can fine tune it. So select
that, go to the `Property Editor` and
I want to give it an angle of
I don’t know, 45 degrees or
56 degrees why not 56
degrees and there we go it’s an
angle of 56 degrees
for the horseshoe shape. So there we
go that’s how we're using these four
different modifications to create a horseshoe shape
gabion wall seating area
And finally I just want to talk to you about
the blocks that we have our disposal
there’s three different types of blocks that
I’ve got, there’s forest garden plants
again you can download these zip files
native wild plants, this is only has
a couple of plants in at the moment
and this project I’m gonna be working
on, and then garden furniture which has
got some useful garden furniture in it
like benches and steps and stuff like
that and people. So I’ll just show
you forest garden plants first of all
So if I click on open
blocks, forest garden and then that’s divided
into five different sections and the forest
garden plants blocks, it’s incomplete but there’s
a spreadsheet that I have created, I’ll
just show you the page first of all
there’s a spreadsheet I’ve created forest garden
bit.ly/forest-garden-spreadsheet and
this has a list of all the
plants in this book and I’ve started
to put all the plants into a
block list so I was doing it anyway
for myself but you're more than welcome
to dip in and help them
out, help
yourself to any of the
trees which are in there so I
don’t know there’s a Crataegus
dilatata, whatever that is, click
it out here so to
get a block out I’ll just show you that
again, select it from the list
the block that you want and
then click on that icon here which
is `Insert Block` and it gives you it out
here. And there you go, Broadleaf Hawthorn, so
I’ll copy that, go back to my
mods
paste it in, there we have a
Broadleaf Hawthorn and there’s, you’ve
got quite a choice of quite a
few plants there. And
then finally for garden furniture, blocks, furniture
again you can download this. This has
got useful things like I don’t know
a deck chair so you can copy
and then just copy and paste it
in and then we’ve got a Broadleaf
Hawthorn and a deck chair, how
lovely is that?
Okay thank you very much for watching
see you in the next section which
is about real world examples, I’ll be doing
a walk through applying all these techniques
and using these blocks in creating two
different types of garden, thanks