Greetings and welcome to section four of my online
class ‘CAD for Gardeners’ and here I’m
going be looking at
a couple of real world examples. First
of all I’m looking at an
average sized garden in the UK
so that you can get an idea
of scale and how that compares to
compares with an acre which is a
traditional UK area of land
Then I’ll be looking at using a
satellite photograph
a screenshot of a satellite photograph
as a background for a CAD
plan which works better with the larger
garden and then the actual
gardens themselves and these are real clients
that I’ve had, ones about an acre for
the garden and ones a town
garden. So the average garden in the
UK is a 188 square metres
apparently, according to the Office of
National Statistics. In London that’s 140
140 square metres and that compares
to an acre which is 4,000 square metres
and you can see here
in this image that there is the
one acre, the one on the left-hand
side and then this garden on the
right-hand side. Should be able to
this is a screenshot that
I did so you can just see
how they compare and forest
gardens do tend to be a
bit larger than your
average garden, mostly because they have
more trees and more people
think about them in
that way but you can have a
forest garden
in a small garden, it’s much more
about the process and the principles than
it is about the actual size
of the garden. So now looking at
a satellite photograph this is a
3D version but we're going to use
the 2D plan. There’s three steps
to using a satellite photograph as a
background for
your CAD plan. First one is to take
a screenshot, then we work out the
metres per pixel and then we import
that image into QCAD. I’ll just quickly go
through that process now and I’ll be
going through this again later for
both examples. First I’ll take a
screenshot. Make sure it’s the highest resolution
possible and
then be sure to include the
scale in metres, you can just about
see that down in the bottom right-hand corner
and save it as a good quality
JPEG. Then you measure the pixel length
of the metres scale, so zooming in
here, that’s 5 metres that scale at
the bottom and you can see it’s
106 pixels, so metres
per pixel, 5 metres divided by
106 pixels gives you
0.047 blah de blah de blah
metres per pixel and that is your
call it image scale factor, that’s how
much you need to scale the image down
because when you import an image
image into QCAD, it imports it at
1 metre per pixel whereas actually we’ve
got 0.047 metres per
pixel here. So that’s the reason for
scaling it and it’s really really important to
do that otherwise all your
measurements will be out
And then we go into QCAD
`File > Import > Select > Select All`
View the `Property Editor`, so that’s
under the `File` menu and this is
where you're bringing in the image, view
the `Property Editor`
which I’ve actually got locked now on the
right-hand side and you want to put
in the width and the height factor
you can just see down there, there’s
a width factor for the
image and the height factor and
in there we enter that number
0.047 that’s a metre
that’s the image scale factor that’s metres
per pixel
So enter them in there
and then that image gets scaled down
Cool, so that’s quite straightforward steps but
can be really really useful having that
satellite photograph in a CAD plan because
it’s really handy guide to have. Obviously
you want to be, you’ve got got to
be aware of there’s copyright issues
you can't use this commercially etc etc
but it’s handy to know how
to do it. Okay so I’m going
to jump straight over into creating the
garden acre example. Jump over into QCAD
I’ll quickly show you how to add a
template so the first thing that we
need to do is to go to
my GitHub
page github.com/growdigital/template
and download that
template, so click on `Code`, `Download ZIP`. Once
that has finished downloading go to your
download folder
and unzip it
unzip it there, I’m going to rename it
template just to keep things tidy
Going to cut that and I have created
in my documents folder I have
created a QCAD folder and that’s
where I’m gonna put my templates so
paste that in there. Now I need
to go back into QCAD
and then under `Edit > Application Preferences > File
and Templates` I need to add that
folder, so go into my Documents folder
into QCAD, into template and then
choose that one, click `OK` it says
you need to restart so we will restart
QCAD
and now when you go `File > New
From Template`
you will see that you have the
default folder here, click on `Template`
`Create New Drawing` there we go and
it’s got all the layers in there
as well. So I’m just going to save
that first of all into the garden
acre folder, save as and
and, where are we? We're here so
call that garden-acre and save
that in there. The next thing I
want to do is to bring in
that satellite photograph so I’ve opened up
GNU Image Manipulation Program which is
like Photoshop, because I’m on Linux I
don’t have Photoshop anymore
use the marquee tool and I’ll select
that area there and that then gives
me down here, gives us the size
of a 114 so that’s
10 metres divided by a 114
pixels and that’s metres per pixel
so 10 metres divided by 114
is 0.08771…
etc so I’ll just
save that number and then I’ll use
that number when I scale down the
image. So go back into CAD, go
`File > Import` garden acre and satellite, so
bring that straight in
oops, okay, and you can see it’s
really really really really really big. What
I want to do is to put
that into the xSatellite layer, so it’s
right at the back, that layer down the bottom
this is the reason
for having layers is that you
can just put different stuff on different
layers and keep it locked up and
tidied away. So now I
need to scale this image down
to the right metres per pixel, it’s
being brought in at 1 meter per pixel
and I need it to be much
considerably smaller, so make sure it’s selected
and then I go to that width
factor and the height factor, let me
just pull it over here a little
bit so you can see, so width
factor I’ll place in the metres per
pixel which are calculated from the Photoshop
file and I’ll paste in that number there
and there we go that’s much more
to scale, okay. Another handy little hint
quite often when you bring in new
images and new elements they’ll sit on
top of everything else so if you
go to `Modify` and then the `Draw Order`
you can send it to the
back and that means that you then
get to see other bits and pieces
like the legend I’ve got down here.
So, I’ve created a template, got the
satellite image in and now I’m going to
create the boundary, so back into QCAD
click on the boundary layer because
this is where I’m going to be
drawing the boundary and this is a
lovely house, I just I do like
it, it’s a nice little job
I wanted to do a a water garden
And I’m going to use `Snap Free`
yep, and then I’m using the
line tool here and `Snap Free` and
then I’m going to trace an outline
and it’s this field you know this
field here, I’m going
to trace an outline around it. It’s
not going to be particularly
accurate or particularly pretty but just gives
you an idea. I could be
using curves for this as well. I
could be doing it accurately too!
There we go and then `Snap Auto` because I
want to snap onto the end of
that bit there okay. There we go
hit escape go back to the arrow
tool. Ah what you can do brilliantly
really nice little feature you can lock
layers so I’m going to lock that satellite layer
and then go back to my boundary layer
This means I don’t pick up
the satellite photo by accident
Now we’ve got that if I
hide, you click on the eye
it hides a layer so I’ll just
hide that layer and you can see
that’s the line that we’ve drawn around
it. So now
if I double-click on it, it selects
it, it gives you the
total length here but it doesn't
give you the area so what I’m
going to do is make it into
a polyline which is what I showed you
earlier on so double-click
selects all the items, `Draw > Polyline >
Polyline From Selection`
And now when I click on it
it gives us an area so that’s
3,127m²
so basically that’s three quarters of an
acre which is a fair sized, nice
sized garden
I’ll bring the satellite back so we
can see. So next I’m going to
put some paths in
and I’ll just do this on
the areas. I’m just going to use
a line tool, I’m not
going do anything really fancy, so line tool
this one here and I know that
there’s an entrance here, I’ll snap onto
the entity so that I know that
it snaps actually onto that line, I think
the path is around about there and
I go `Snap Auto` turns it off and
I think they want a
path going around here
round the top
and there’s another exit out there, so
`Snap onto Entity` to snap up to
there, there we go
We now have a path going around
the edge. Turn off the satellite so
you can see the path. What I
will do is to offset this so
you get much more the idea of
a path, so using the offset tool
you can draw one line for your
path and then you can offset it
both sides or one side and
then it creates
the path itself but the size of
your path depends on how wide
you want it but if it’s about
a metre, a metre’s a nice big comfortable path
down to about 0.4 metres
for a single person to walk along
so it depends where the path is and
how you’re using it and so let’s hit escape
go into the modification tools and then offset
and I’ll offset 0.3 metres
on each side I’ll just zoom in
so offset it on that side and
offset it on that side, okay and
then I’m going to delete the middle
bit. And then you’ve got a nice
little path. Now you could do this using
the NURBS tool as well. Then next
up, I want to
put the trees in so let’s go
and grab some trees from the forest
garden blocks. Go back up here, blocks
forest garden canopy and let’s get a selection
of trees. Cornus capitata, Cornel…
Cornus capitata, click that button there
check that one Bentham's Cornel, Cornus kousa
just escape that, Cornus kousa, click on
the insert block button, it’s a Chinese Dogwood
I’ve got to have a hawthorn
Crataegus schraderiana
insert block, Blue Hawthorn
and then I always always always have to
have a Sweet Chestnut, actually a Sweet
Chestnut won't work because I know it’s
a damp, oh I’ll put a Sweet Chestnut on anyway
let’s pretend it’s not damp there, Sweet
Chestnuts don’t like heavy clay soils
and I know it’s a heavy
clay soil there so it won't do
very well. I’ll just cut them
and I’ll go over to the tree
layer in the `Layers List` and
then paste and there we go, look
at that, fantastic and then you move the
trees around so that they’re in
the right position
they've got enough spacing and there’s enough
there’s enough spacing around between
the trees and enough light getting through
to the bottom canopy floor layer
Okay now I’m going to put
in some hedgerows, some hedges so let’s
open up
the shrub document from the forest garden
plants
and we’ll have a hedge of
Ligustrum vulgare
this is a Wild Privet really really
good wildlife plant, Privet, Ligustrum vulgare
and we go back here and paste
it in
and this forms part of the
design side of things is what
height windbreak you should have
So on the northside you can see, down
here you’ve got north-east-west and
south, on the north side you want
the tallest wind breaks along there and
also because that is a road
there as well you want a
big tall I would have put a
double thickness windbreak along there, you're
not going to lose any light, you
get much more protection and you make
it thick and right cut down on
the amount of road noise that you
get. So Ligustrum vulgare is actually
not that tall so I wouldn't have
it, 1.5 metres
I thought it would be bigger
than that, to 1.5 to
2 metres
so that’s a kind of hedge you'd
have on the south side. So the
most valuable sunlight comes from the south
and the west that the air has
had a time to warm up in
the afternoon so that the afternoon
sunlight is more valuable, there’s more photosynthesis
apparently than in the
morning. I want to put them onto the
shrub layer
I put one there
and then one there
okay
And then to make it a windbreak
hedge all that I do
it’s three metres diameter
all that I’m going do now is
to draw a line between them, right
in the centre, the central points, it
should automatically snap to the reference point
which is in the middle
from one to the other. Hit escape and
now I’m going to use the offset
tool to put the two sides of
the hedge on. So the same
kind of principle as creating a path
so modification tools, offset tool and I
know that the width of the Privet
hedge will be 3 metres diameter
or 3 metres width, so it’s
1.5 metres for one side
1.5 metres for the other side
So a distance 1.5
bomp and that one bomp
Delete the middle one now
There you go, we now have
a windbreak. And then I would
do wind breaks around the
edges. A big part of the design
is figuring out how the different areas
are going to be used and a
fundamental element of that design which I
cover in my design class is creating
the areas through the use of paths
So you create
the paths first, you create the structure
of the garden first of all and
then you can bring in the different
planting around and the features around that
okay so what I would do
after this I would create
different windbreaks all the way around so
you would always want to have
windbreaks surrounding your garden to reduce
the amount of turbulence particularly with
the Climate Emergency because there’s going to
be more and more extreme weather events
There we go and that’s that
one done. And now onto creating the
garden town
So as I said before, the satellite
really is just a rough guide. I’ll
do it from the satellite now but what
you want to be doing is creating
your plan from actual measurements on the
ground and just get general information from
the maps, okay, so this is what
we're going to be doing so let’s go
and create a new file, save that
one, create a new file from template
And I’m going to save that as garden
town, okay, go up the level, garden town
and this is garden town,
garden-town
great stuff then go over to
my image bitmap editor, zoom down
here
Use a rectangular marquee tool and select that
and you can see that the width
the marquee is a 110 pixels
so that is 5 metres and
110 pixels that’s
5 divided by 110 gives
you your metres per pixel, so
5 divided by 110
gives you that.
Lovely. And now go back into QCAD
select the satellite layer, file import and
it’s going to make me go all the
way back obviously
examples, garden town, satellite
pop that in there
See, really really really big it is
Let’s select it and then the width
factor, whoops, I’ll just pop that up here
for you
that’s the width factor here, so paste
in that value which is the metres
per pixel, paste that value in there
and you can see it shrinks right the
way down, weeee, that’s better, and now
it’s to scale and then just to
get it, can you see
`Modify > Draw Order > Send to Back`
and then you can see
the
compass, the legend there as well lovely
I’ll lock that layer
So this is a friend's garden in
North London, I worked on a few
years ago now
okay, going to pop the `Property Editor`
there and it’s this one here, so
I’m just going to do this really
really really basically so start off with
the boundary so select the boundary layer
click on the line tool, this one
the only one I ever use
`LI` and then we’ll just click
click, click, click, click, and that’s it
double-click it and you can see
if I just turn off the satellite
that’s it, it’s a bit rough and ready
double-click it and then we’ll turn
that into a polyline and then we
can see how big it is, so
`Draw Polyline From Selection`
and that gives me an area of
102 metres, so that’s
how big their garden is
so it’s a bit under the
average, the average for a UK London garden
is a 140 square metres
and theirs comes in at just over
100 square metres okay
so then what I would do is
to put the path in
in areas and this is where sometimes
you want to change the colours of
your layers so you can actually see
what's going on, as you can see
from this you can hardly,
you can't actually see the red
on that boundary on this particular image
so this is where you would play
around with the different colours, so we’ll get
the, ah the kitchen door is around
about here somewhere
and say oh we want a new
path and that path goes up to
here
up to the shed
okay
let’s just turn off that satellite
so you can see what's going on
so that’s my path
I’ll make it into a polyline so it’s
easier to use so `Draw > Polyline
Polyline From Selection` and that sets it as
a group
and then
oh let’s go and put the the
shed in, there’s a shed down here
in the bottom left-hand corner so
I’ll go into my shape tools
and I’ll just draw it freehand
so `Snap Free` so it
doesn't snap onto anything else
I’ll do that there, there we go I’ve
gone and drawn it into the
areas layer, so how you move
it in the `Property Editor` is to
select the thing that you want
to move and then change the
the layer that it’s in. I
want to put it into the Structures
layer and there you will see, it will
automatically change colour down here, we just
turn off the satellite so you can
see, okay? Double-click it, I’ll turn it
into a block actually `Create Block
From Selection`
Okay and I’m going to call that shed and
then you’ll see
the shed will appear here in the
`Block List`, okay?
And then it’s the same principle now
as well for putting in trees and
shrubs I’ve got my forest
garden plants blocks here, I’ll put up
a hazel down here, Corylus avellana so
the big name’s the common name
and then the botanical name’s underneath
and the botanical names is
in the list, in the `Layer List`
so let’s cut that
go over to the garden town go
to shrub
paste it in there, wow, much much
bigger it’s a town garden so the
trees obviously much larger size, so there
we go and then you can do
that with individual beds with the paths
putting plants in, putting different features in
greenhouses, patios, all that kind
of stuff, then you start to build
up the design for the garden but
as I said before, the most important
thing when you're creating these designs is
to get the spacing right between the
trees, make sure that they've
got the paths in the right
place, so getting the structure in the
The smaller planting is much much easier
to do
on-site so you don’t have
to be so precise about
the designs for them but
it’s really really important to get the
trees and the paths and the main
structures in place first. And that brings us
to a close and what I also have
a whole load of resources, so there’s the
link for downloading
QCAD, they've got the CAD files
for this class, I’ve also created
a public Telegram group called Garden Wild Edible
which goes along with these classes
and that’s a space if you want
to ask any questions, then feel free
to join and then ask questions
if you’ve got any questions about QCAD
kind of technical
stuff then there’s a QCAD
link to QCAD forum, there’s my template
my delicious CAD template file
native plants spreadsheet which I haven't shown
you which I ought to show you
and the forest garden spreadsheet
I will be using these more
in the design section of
the classes. So the Garden Wild Spreadsheet
is a list of native plants, it’s
flowers just at the moment, I’ve got
space for other native forms but the
Forest Garden Spreadsheet is a list of
all the forest garden plants in
Martin Crawford's book as well so loads and
loads of information there and then you’ve
got my CAD blocks too
That draws us to an end
I hope that’s useful, if you do want
to get in touch with me, my
email address is here
hello@natureworks.org.uk and you
can sign up for my newsletter as
well. Thank you very much, see you
again soon, cheers, bye!